A Guide to the Correspondence and Subject Files of the Virginia Secretary of Transportation, 1994-1997
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Correspondence and Subject Files of the Virginia Secretary of Transportation, 1994-1997
The Library of Virginia
35872
2 cu. ft.
Virginia. Office of the Secretary of Transportation
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was transferred by records manager, Cathy M. Ghidotti, 19 November 1997.
Biographical Information
In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" to assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties. Compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governors top management team or "secretariats," as they are called now.
Governor Linwood Holton's top priority for the 1972 session of the General Assembly was a proposal for a Governor's Cabinet, reorganizing state agencies into six major departments--each headed by a secretary appointed by the governor. Transportation and public safety was one of these six departments. The office of Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was created on April 8, 1972, by an act passed by the General Assembly. Governor Holton appointed Wayne A. Whitham, a member of the Winchester City Council, as the first Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety. When Whitham took office on July 1, 1972, he was responsible for State Highway Commission, Division of Motor Vehicles, Department of State Police, Highway Safety Division, Office of Emergency Services, Department of Military Affairs, Virginia State Crime Commission and the Law Enforcement Officers Training Standards Commission. The Office has undergone a series of administrative reorganizations since. On April 12, 1976, the Legislature established separate secretariats for transportation and for public safety, effective July 1, 1976. On July 1, 1984, the offices were again combined. Most recently, the Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was divided into separate secretariats on February 22, 1990. The Secretary of Transportation is a member of the Governor's Cabinet, and is appointed by the governor, subject to confirmation by the General Assembly. The Secretary is responsible to the governor for the Department of Transportation, Department of Rail and Public Transportation, Department of Aviation, Department of Motor Vehicles, Virginia Port Authority and the Motor Vehicle Dealers Board.
Wayne A. Whitham, the first Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety, was reappointed by Governor-elect Miles E. Godwin, Jr., in December 1973 and by Governor-elect John N. Dalton in December 1977. Whitham suffered a heart attack in August 1978 and resigned in December 1978. On June 7, 1984, Whitham died in Richmond, Virginia. Governor Dalton named George M. Walters, a former top executive of the Reynolds Metals Corporation, to succeed Whitham as Secretary of Transportation. Walters served until the end of Dalton's term in January 1982. Governor-elect Charles S. Robb, the first Democrat to be elected governor since 1965, did not retain any of Dalton's cabinet secretaries. Robb appointed Andrew B. Fogarty, Dalton's assistant secretary for financial policy, as Secretary of Transportation. On July 1, 1984, the secretariats of transportation and public safety were combined again. As a result this partial reorganization of state government, Governor Robb appointed Fogarty Secretary of Administration and Franklin E. White, Secretary of Public Safety, assumed Fogarty's Transportation duties. White, who served as a White House liaison official under President Jimmy Carter, resigned in June 1985 to become the New York state commissioner of transportation. He was replaced by Andrew Fogarty who served until the end of the Robb administration. He later served as Governor Gerald L. Baliles chief of staff from August 1986 to October 1989 when he resigned to become a vice president with CSX Corporation.
In December 1985, Governor-elect Gerald L. Baliles, picked Vivian E. Watts, a northern Virginia legislator, as Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety. Watts served until the end of Baliles' term in 1990. In 1995 she was elected to her old seat in the Virginia House of Delegates. On February 22, 1990, the Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was divided into separate secretariats. Governor L. Douglas Wilder, appointed John G. Milliken, a member of the Arlington County Board of Supervisors, as the Secretary of Transportation. Milliken resigned on December 17, 1993.
In February 1994 Governor George Allen, the first Republican elected governor since 1977, appointed Robert Martinez as Secretary of Transportation. Martinez was born in Cuba and had served as Deputy Administrator for the Marine Administration and Associate Deputy Secretary of Transportation during President George H.W. Bush's administration. At the end of Governor Allen's term in January 1998, Martinez joined the Norfolk Southern Corporation. Shirley Ybarra, deputy Secretary of Transportation in the Allen administration, was named Martinez's successor by Governor-elect James Gilmore. Ybarra previously worked as a special assistant to Transportation Secretary Elizabeth Dole during President Ronald Reagan's administration. Ybarra served until the end of Gilmore's administration in January 2002. Whittington W. Clement, a former lawyer and long-time member of the Virginia House of Delegates representing the City of Danville, was appointed Secretary of Transportation by Governor Mark R. Warner in 2002. Pierce R. Homer, Deputy Secretary of Transportation, replaced Clement in 2005.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of memorandums related to transportation in Virginia, all materials fall under the headings of Virginia Port Authority, Department of Motor Vehicles, Department of Rail and Public Transportation, Department of Aviation, Highways and Corridors, Speeches, Department of Transportationa nd General Secretariat files.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence and Suject Files
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files, 1994-1997., Extent: 2 cu. ft. (2 boxes). (Box 1-2)
  Arrangement created by agency has been maintained, files are alphabetical under each sub heading.
  - Virginia Port Authority: Bonds, 1996. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Port Authority: Bonds, 1997. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Port Authority: Corps of Engineers, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Port Authority: Crany Island, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Port Authority: Dredging - James River, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Port Authority: Dredging - York River, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Port Authority: Foreign Trade Zones, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Virginia Port Authority: Inland Port, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Virginia Port Authority: Intermodal Installation Project, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Virginia Port Authority: Maersk/Sea Land, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Port Authority: Procurement, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Motor Vehicles, Department of: Accomplishments, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Motor Vehicles, Department of: Auto Theft Unit, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Motor Vehicles, DMV "Connections", 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Motor Vehicles, Department of: Customer Service Centers, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Motor Vehicles, Department of: District Alignment, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Motor Vehicles, Department of: Emissions Inspections, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Motor Vehicles, Department of: License Plate Production, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Motor Vehicles, Department of: One Stop Shopping, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Motor Vehicles, Department of: Salvage Vehicle Legislation (Federal), 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Motor Vehicles, Department of: Series/1 Replacement, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Motor Vehicles, Department of: Special License Plates, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Motor Vehicles, Department of: Trucking Task Force, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Motor Vehicles, Department of: VIPNet, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Rail and Public Transportation, Department of: Bus Transit Privatization, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Rail and Public Transportation, Department of: High Speed Rail, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Rail and Public Transportation, Department of: Virginia Railway Express, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Aviation, Department of: Air and Space Annex, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Aviation, Department of: Air Service, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Aviation, Department of: ARNAV Datalink, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Aviation, Department of: Eastern Virginia Air System Study, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Aviation, Department of: Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority (MWAA), 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Aviation, Department of: Regulations, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Aviation, Department of: Richmond International Airport, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Aviation, Department of: State Aircraft Use, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Aviation, Department of: Tangier Island Airport, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Aviation, Department of: US-UK Open Skies, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Highways and Corridors: Coalfields Expressway, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Highways and Corridors: Corridor H, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Highways and Corridors: Dulles Toll Road, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Highways and Corridors: Fairfax County Parkway, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Highways and Corridors: Norfolk-Virginia Beach Expressway, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Highways and Corridors: Oak Grove Connector, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Highways and Corridors: Snickersville Turnpike, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Highways and Corridors: Southeatern Expressway, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Highways and Corridors: Route 17, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Highways and Corridors: Route 29 - Charlottesville Bypass, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Highways and Corridors: Route 43Y - Eagle Rock Bridge, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Highways and Corridors: Interstate 66, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Highways and Corridors: Interstate 66 - Major Investment Study, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Highways and Corridors: Interstate 73, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Highways and Corridors: Interstate 95 - Pavement Issue, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Highways and Corridors: Route 168, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Highways and Corridors: Route 234 Bypass, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Highways and Corridors: Route 288, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Highways and Corridors: Route 460, 1996-1997. (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Speeches, 1997. (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Speeches, 1996. (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Speeches, 1995. (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Speeches, 1994. (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Transportation, Department of: Alternative Fuels Revolving Fund, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Transportation, Department of: Bonds, 1995;1997. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Transportation, Department of: Coleman Bridge, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Transportation, Department of: Crumb Rubber, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Transportation, Department of: Demonstration Projects, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Transportation, Department of: Disadvantaged Business Enterprise, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Transportation, Department of: Enhancements, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Transportation, Department of: Fastoll, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Transportation, Department of: Federal Funds, Additional, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Transportation, Department of: High Occupancy Vehicle Lanes (HOV-2), 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Transportation, Department of: Inmate Labor, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Transportation, Department of: Metropolitan Washington Regional Transit Authority, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Transportation, Department of: National Transportation System, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Transportation, Department of: North Carolina, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Transportation, Department of: Northern Virginia District - VDOT Building, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Transportation, Department of: Northern Virginia District - Maintenance Complex, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Transportation, Department of: Ohio Plan, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Transportation, Department of: Outdoor Advertising, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Transportation, Department of: Ozone Transport Commission, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Transportation, Department of: Privatization (1), 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Transportation, Department of: Regional Design Centers, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Transportation, Department of: Rest Areas, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Transportation, Department of: Six Year Plan, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Transportation, Department of: Smart Road, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Transportation, Department of: State Infrastructure Banks, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Transportation, Department of: State Vehicle Fleet, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Transportation, Department of: Statewide Intermodal Long Range Plan, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Transportation, Department of: Telecommunications/Accommodation Policy, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Transportation, Department of: Transportation Coordination Council, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Transportation, Department of: Truck Access - Route 15, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Transportation, Department of: Woodrow Wilson Bridge, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - General Secretariat Files: Air Quality, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - General Secretariat Files: Blue Ribbon Strike Force, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - General Secretariat Files: Budget, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - General Secretariat Files: Customer Service, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - General Secretariat Files: Commercial Vehicle Information System and Network project, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - General Secretariat Files: Debt Capacity, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - General Secretariat Files: Drug Testing, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - General Secretariat Files: Federal Mandates, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - General Secretariat Files: House Joint Resolution 160, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - General Secretariat Files: Intermodal Coordinating Council, Establishment of, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - General Secretariat Files: National Highway System, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - General Secretariat Files: Needs Assessment, 20 year, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - General Secretariat Files: National Economic Crossroads Transportation Efficiency Act, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - General Secretariat Files: Privatization (2), 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - General Secretariat Files: Reauthorization of Intermodal Surface Transportation Efficiency Act, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - General Secretariat Files: Senate Joint Resolution 143 and 240, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 47-48)
  - General Secretariat Files: Southern Governor's Association, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - General Secretariat Files: STEP 21, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - General Secretariat Files: Urban Initiatives, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - General Secretariat Files: Virginia Aviation Conference, 1997 Aug 21. (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - General Secretariat Files: Virginia Connections, 1996-1997. (Box 2, Folder 53)